<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>Mosab Ahmad Ibrahim - cycling</title>
      <link>https://mosab.co.uk</link>
      <description>an oddly wired brain!</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://mosab.co.uk/tags/cycling/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Joining the Tour De Ricky 200km Ride: A New Adventure Awaits!</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://mosab.co.uk/blog/tour-de-ricky-2024/</link>
          <guid>https://mosab.co.uk/blog/tour-de-ricky-2024/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mosab.co.uk/blog/tour-de-ricky-2024/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mosab.co.uk&#x2F;blog&#x2F;tour-de-ricky-2024&#x2F;tour-de-ricky-2024-banner.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tour De Ricky 2024 Banner&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am beyond excited to announce that I will be participating in the Tour De Ricky 200km (approximately 125 miles) ride event in 2024! As a beginner, yet passionate cyclist, I have always been drawn to challenging myself and pushing my limits (whenever I got time away from my job and other responsibilities), and this event promises to be an unforgettable experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-tour-de-ricky&quot;&gt;What is Tour De Ricky?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tour De Ricky is an Audax event, part of Audax UK, a organization that promotes long-distance cycling events.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is an Audax ride, you ask me? No better answer than what Audax UK&#x27;s website itself &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.audax.uk&#x2F;about-audax&#x2F;new-to-audax&#x2F;&quot;&gt;has to say&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, from which I quote:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Audax ride - known internationally as a Randonnée - is a cycle ride that has to be completed within a set time limit, including any stops to eat or rest. In most cases, riders have to maintain a minimum speed of 15km&#x2F;h (some particularly long or hilly rides have a slightly lower minimum speed) and importantly a maximum speed of 30km&#x2F;h. That&#x27;s a little under 10mph and 20mph in Imperial measures.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s not a race and individual riders&#x27; times are not published; if you finish within the time limit, you&#x27;ve succeeded.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Riders are expected to be self-sufficient. That doesn&#x27;t mean that you have to ride alone or that you can&#x27;t call on the services of a village blacksmith to help weld your frame back together, should the worst happen, but you navigate for yourself and if you do have any mechanical problems along the way, it&#x27;s down to you to sort them or get yourself home.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some rides offer food along the way; more often, you&#x27;ll be finding your own sources of fuel, from cafes and pubs to village shops and service stations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in the hills, the British weather and distances ranging from 50km to 1400km and what might have sounded like a simple bike ride becomes more of a challenge - one that is appealing to increasing numbers of cyclists year on year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also watch this great video explaining what Audax is:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aspect-w-16 aspect-h-9&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
    src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;qreIQjtClbw?si=mXe6uLa_nD2WO8Bq&quot;
    title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
    allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen
    allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tour De Ricky event in particular offers a range of routes, 50km, 100km, and 200km long in distance, but I have set my sights on the 200km challenge. This particular route promises a full day of excitement, with a mix of rolling hills, scenic countryside, and quiet roads.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-200km-route-a-challenge-awaits&quot;&gt;The 200km Route: A Challenge Awaits&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 200km route is designed to test the rider&#x27;s endurance and cycling skills. With a total elevation gain of 2,500 meters, I will need to be prepared for this ride, since it has been a long time with me out of the saddle, and in a relatively short period of time too (4-5 weeks). The route will take the riders through some of the most beautiful landscapes in the country, with picturesque villages, ancient woodlands, and stunning views of the surrounding countryside.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-m-excited&quot;&gt;Why I&#x27;m Excited&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m excited to join the Tour De Ricky 200km bike ride for several reasons.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I love the sense of community that comes with participating in a mass cycling event that is not competitive in nature (i.e. it is not a race). I&#x27;m looking forward to meeting fellow cyclists, sharing stories, and making new friends.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I&#x27;m eager to challenge myself and push my limits. Completing this event will be a huge achievement, and I&#x27;m excited to see how far I can push myself. Finally, I&#x27;m looking forward to the scenic route and the opportunity to explore new parts of the country.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, I have participated in the 100km ride in 2022, and it is still my longest ride so far (~120km). I did not get back to the start within the event&#x27;s time limit, and I even lost my Brevit! So it was not counted as a success in Audax UK records (although it is a huge success in my personal records), so I am determined to get to the finish line within the time limit this year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;training-and-preparation&quot;&gt;Training and Preparation&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mosab.co.uk&#x2F;blog&#x2F;tour-de-ricky-2024&#x2F;training-plan.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Plan&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&#x27;m excited, I&#x27;m also aware that this event requires careful preparation and training. Over the coming weeks and months, I will be putting in the miles, honing my cycling skills, and building up my endurance. I will be working on my bike, making sure it&#x27;s in top condition, and preparing myself mentally and physically for the challenge ahead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above is a hand drawn&#x2F;written training calendar that fits my current work schedule (with return to office et al), and hopefully I can manage to finish it. It is not enough, but it will have to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also discovered that the ride day will be in one of my oncall shifts, so I will have to find a swap for that! :D&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tour De Ricky 200km ride, if successful, will be my first Century Ride, a ride that is a 100 miles long, or more, and will be a dream come true for me. I have done a &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mosab.co.uk&#x2F;blog&#x2F;first-metric-century&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Metric Centry&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; before, also with Tour De Ricky. I&#x27;m excited to be part of this amazing event once again, to challenge myself, and to experience the thrill of long-distance cycling. If you&#x27;re a fellow cyclist, I encourage you to join me on this adventure. Let&#x27;s ride together and make some unforgettable memories!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;useful-links&quot;&gt;Useful Links:&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tourdericky.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tour De Ricky Website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tourdericky.uk&#x2F;200km-a-full-day-of-challenge&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tour De Ricky 200km Route&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.audax.uk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Audax UK Website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>My First Metric Century</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://mosab.co.uk/blog/first-metric-century/</link>
          <guid>https://mosab.co.uk/blog/first-metric-century/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://mosab.co.uk/blog/first-metric-century/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mosab.co.uk&#x2F;blog&#x2F;first-metric-century&#x2F;audax-brevet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Audax Tour De Ricky&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I finished my first &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;metric century&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (a ride that is 100km or more)! Was riding in &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tour De
Ricky&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; audax, and it was a challenging route for me. Took me 7 hours and 22 minutes of riding (10
hours if you include the cafe and rest stops) but I did it!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distance: 119.8 km
Elevation Gain: 1134 m
Time: 7h 22m&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mosab.co.uk&#x2F;blog&#x2F;first-metric-century&#x2F;metric-century-strava.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Metric Century Stats&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some lessons I learned from this ride are (in a very raw format, will iterate on them later):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed specific recommendations in regards to what to wear, and most resources talk guidelines,
which is something you don&#x27;t want for the first few rides. In order to be able to take a guideline,
you need to have tried a few rides in different conditions first. I wanted specifics (like wear a
bibshort if it 10 degrees celsius or above, etc).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I definitely need more gears for those hills&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great knowing my FTP, as I could only finish the ride by actively trying to keep my power
below the FTP especially on those hill.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.1. That required better shifting for the gears, and that&#x27;s something I have always heard, but never
really understood&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.2. I also don&#x27;t know if I was crossing the chains, will need to see&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.3. This is one of the areas that people might benefit from videos on how to change the gears and in
what order just like car drivers have&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I DEFINITELY need to increase my FTP&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was lucky that I did not have any punctures, or mechanicals, but it was assuring that I got tools
with me&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The back bag probably shouldn&#x27;t have been there (over worrying about the weather made me pack extra
just in case)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably should&#x27;ve taken the power bank. Phones almost died at the end&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a rear freehub that needs changing (there is play in the cassette) but there is nothing I
could do about it, as the part was delivered right before the ride. Was afraid it fails on me during
the ride, and paid extra attention not to put sudden impact on the drivetrain, luckily it didn&#x27;t
fail!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the route on multiple devices was helpful&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cycling navigation experience could use a lot of improvement. This is not a solved problem yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investing in a bike fit was one of the best things I did! Can&#x27;t imagine doing this distance with the
original bike setup I got!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Servicing the bike, and changing the worn chain was also a contributing factor to minimise the risk
of getting a mechanical, I guess!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should&#x27;ve planned the transportation to and from the start&#x2F;finish point better! That cost me a
late start, and because of that I ended up doing the whole route alone instead of doing it with a
bunch of fellow colleagues, but that&#x27;s ok.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mosab.co.uk&#x2F;blog&#x2F;first-metric-century&#x2F;metric-century-finish-line.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Me at the finish line&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a video about the ride:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aspect-w-16 aspect-h-9&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
    src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;uhsU0AqyNgM?si=mXe6uLa_nD2WO8Bq&quot;
    title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
    allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen
    allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
